<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Website Review | Eric Dykstra's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.ericdykstra.me/blog/categories/website-review/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.ericdykstra.me/"/>
  <updated>2012-09-10T13:25:31-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.ericdykstra.me/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Eric Dykstra]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[eric@ericdykstra.me]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Don't be a Blind Copycat: Why Good Web Design Starts with Product Goals]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.ericdykstra.me/blog/2012/09/10/dont-be-a-blind-copycat-why-good-web-design-starts-with-product-goals/"/>
    <updated>2012-09-10T13:16:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.ericdykstra.me/blog/2012/09/10/dont-be-a-blind-copycat-why-good-web-design-starts-with-product-goals</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>A user interface is the product of a design. A design is a set of decisions about a particular product. Those decisions represent the product's goals and ambitions.</em> - Rebekah Cox, Product Designer at Quora from <a href="http://artypapers.com/ap.log/thread.php?346">"Early Quora Design Notes"</a></p>

<p>It's no secret; the latest web design trends often find their way into a large portion of any new website that comes up. But just because "everybody's doing it" doesn't mean it's the right direction for the website you're working on, or the one your client wants. Does it make sense for <em>every</em> product to have a website that is just one page with just a logo, email form, and giant background image pre-launch? The problem with design trends is that they are copied beyond the case that they were originally made for, and the "goals and ambitions" of the website don't match the design and user interface.</p>

<p>Take the <a href="https://squareup.com">Square website</a> for example: Square is a young company with an innovative product, and just looking at their website tells you what their product does <em>in an instant</em>. I'm not going to say that Paypal ripped them off, but <a href="https://www.paypal.com/">their website</a> redesign is very similar, albeit a much more generic styling. Paypal is not Square, Paypal is a well-established brand, and having a similar homepage for Paypal doesn't make sense. Although they may be trying to sell visitors on one of their new services, it's no excuse to focus user attention on something that very few people are likely interested in. Most people are going to the Paypal website to get to their account and manage it. Even ignoring that fact, their generic call-to-action style banner is not effective. Let's compare and contrast the messaging on those two homepages.</p>

<p>The imagery on the Square homepage of someone using the product is very well-composed and shot nicely, and gives a great introduction to what the product looks like and how it's used. "Start accepting credit cards today." is the headline. The simplest way to explain what the product <em>does</em>. Then the smaller text below: "Sign up and we’ll mail you a free Square Card Reader." which is a brilliantly simple call to action. It's impossible to go to the Square homepage and not understand what the product does.</p>

<p>Paypal, on the other hand, starts with an image of an iPhone, two mugs, and salt and pepper shakers, with one mug on top of a bill. Even within the context of Paypal the company, the messaging isn't initially clear. If you notice the somewhat subtle bill under one of the mugs you may think "oh, maybe it's two friends that went out for coffee, one payed the bill and the other one sent money with Paypal." I'm not sure if this is the purpose of the imagery, but I doubt most people look at the picture long enough to figure it out. Next, we get to the headline: "An ATM is more convenient when it's in your pocket." What? I use an ATM to get cash so that I can buy things at places that don't take a credit card; that has nothing to do with my phone or an app. Then the text beneath: "Send money to anyone from anywhere with the free PayPal mobile app." What does this have to do with an ATM in my pocket? Is the Paypal app supposed to replace me going to an ATM to get cash?</p>

<p>This is a great example of one company following closely a design of another in the same industry, and completely missing the mark design-wise. Design decisions should represent the product's goals and ambitions, rather than just be a function of design trends. Maybe your client came up to you and said "I want you to make our website look like [insert industry leader here]'s website". Sometimes it can work out alright, because presumably these trends exist because they work for some subset of websites, but starting with the design without thinking about the focus of the website will lead you down the same road as Paypal.</p>

<p>Starting with the product's goals and ambitions, whether it's a website about a product like Square, or a website that is a product like Quora, leads to the best user experience. Copying web design trends or, worse, mimicking another site element-for-element skips the most important part of the design process. Next week I'll take an in-depth look into the design of Quora's news feed page, which is one of my favorite examples of a page that produces relevant content (good product focus) without unnecessary clutter, and have some innovative UX that is still intuitive and doesn't break user expectation.</p>

<p>Let me know what you think in the comments or via <a href="mailto:eric@ericdykstra.me">email</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
